<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lettuce Be Cereal</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2020 07:20:26 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2020 07:20:26 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.7.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Technology is magic</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The soul of wit may become the very body of untruth. However elegant and memorable, brevity can never, in the nature of things, do justice to all the facts of a complex situation. On such a theme one can be brief only by omission and simplification. Omission and simplification help us to understand - but help us, in many cases, to understand the wrong thing; for our comprehension may be only of the abbreviator’s neatly formulated notions, not of the vast, ramifying reality from which these notions have been so arbitrarily abstracted”  ― Aldous Huxley, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/work/quotes/16335101&quot;&gt;Brave New World Revisited&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re home late after a grueling day at the office. The light of the sun has given way to the orange common of street light. No one wanders the streets except those few young souls for whom the night is when their soul comes alive. You envy them their energy, and would wish them a good time tonight were your mind not entirely enveloped by the hunger consuming your thoughts. You need to eat something, immediately. Your stomach commands you. You drop your backpack near the entrance and rush towards the kitchen. You’re too tired to make dinner, and too hungry to be choosy about what to eat. If there’s something, anything, that looks even remotely edible that’ll be the dinner for tonight. You open the refrigerator door, and praise the gods and all the luck they shower upon you, there’s some chilli con carne left over, your favorite. Saliva floods your mouth as you grab the container and pour the earthly brown sludge on a plate with some leftover rice. You splash both with copious amounts of hot sauce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re about to dive in when a pang of guilt hits you. You have nothing against eating cold food, and you’re certainly hungry enough to send all decorum to hell, but the microwave is right there in front of you, staring at you, judging you for the slob you’re about to show you are if you do not heat your almost frozen food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You pull the silver door of the microwave open in resignation, and put the plate inside. You close the door and push the button enough times for the microwave to make your food sizzle in its own heat. The light turns on; the plate begins to spin. With nothing to do now but wait, the heaviness of your eyelids starts making itself felt. It too wants its voice heard in the court of your mind. Images of your bed, with you in it, flash through your mind. To sleep and to eat, those are the two directives that now rule your actions, all the complexity of what it means to be a human being simplified into a binary choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re standing in front of the microwave with your forehead glued to the tempered glass of the microwave watching as little pockets of steam start bubbling towards the surface of the chilli’s sauce. You can almost feel the heat coming out of the food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beep… beep… beep…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The light turns off, and the microwave’s shrill announcement wakes you out from your sleepy stupor. That’s when it hits you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve just seen magic happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible that sleepiness has begun taking its toll on your mental capacities, yet there’s this overwhelming feeling that indeed it was magic what you’ve just witnessed. What else would you call it? You open the door and pick the plate up. It is hot to the touch. You bring it over to the dinner table and gingerly guide a fork filled with food into your mouth. You have to be careful about it, blowing on it lest it scorch your tongue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not five minutes before it was almost solid from the cold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You grabbed a plastic container out of the refrigerator, placed the food into a silver machine, and watched as with time it became hot without once you seeing anything happen to it. You were starting at it, it was right in front of you. Nothing touched it, it just sat there, slowly spinning first to one side and then the other, repeating that pattern until the beep beep sound announcing that the magician had just left the stage.  What else could this be but a nifty magic trick, not unlike when a magician pulls a rabbit from the top hat without anyone noticing how it got it there?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you’re a smart person. You know it’s not literally magic that’s heated your food. It was the waves, the electromagnetic waves that did the trick. But that’s hardly a better explanation for what happened. What are electromagnetic waves but another name for magic. Even so, notwithstanding the semantic trick of it, you know how it all is supposed to work. Your student days might be long behind you but you can still recall the basics of how a microwave works. You can almost see it in your mind’s eye, the way the electromagnetic field forces the polarized water molecules to align with it, just as a paper boat aligns with the river current driving it forward. When the field changes direction, so too do the water molecules, and in your mental world you watch as billions and billions of tiny molecules are forced out of their frozen slumber and begin moving furiously and bumping into each other in energetic collisions releasing heat. Thus is your food heated, in a fiery mosh pit of molecules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This mental model pleases you. You revel in what it reveals about your mastery of the natural world, the adeptness with which you can grasp what to others might well have been actual magic. You are the illuminated being who sees behind the veil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet this magnanimous feeling is quickly shattered into a million pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does the microwave generate these waves? You have no idea. What even is an electromagnetic wave in the first place? Mental white noise answers your question. What does it mean to say that the electromagnetic field changes direction? How does that happen? These, and many other questions, flood into your mind and leave you stumped. You could, with some effort, give some tentative answers to some of them, but they do not satisfy you. You know your answers to be wrong, that you’re grasping at straws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have no idea what you’re talking about, and thus you’re left standing at the dinner table, looking at your cooling food in a state of transfixed stupor, the illusion of understanding having peeled away to reveal the extent of your ignorance. You look at the chairs around you and imagine them filled with your many friends. You imagine them asking you the questions you just asked yourself, and that mental picture of being at a loss for words returns. Were they to ask, you wouldn’t be able to explain to them what happens the moment you push the button until your food comes out the other side with curls of steam rising from within. I mean, not really. You could tell them the pretty story you’ve just told yourself, of waves and polar molecules, of furious clashes and hot food, but so too could a parrot. And at least the parrot would be far more entertaining to listen to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parrot would also not confuse his parroting with an actual understanding of the world. Whereas the parrot doesn’t imbue the words he mouths off with any sort relation with the world which they supposedly refer to, you mistake the real world for the words and concepts you use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parrot says the sky is blue, but he doesn’t mean it. It would just as happily say “the elephant is pink”. When you say “a microwave works using dielectric heating”, you think that says something that’s true about the world, that those words contain the world within them. Your explanation of waves, changes in direction, and heat are taken to be full explanations of reality, when in fact they have but tenuous connection with what actually happens when you turn the microwave on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is in these moments of wonder that the veil is lifted and you see through the other side, when you come to terms with the sparseness of your mental models, the heuristical nature of them which gives them their usefulness but which ultimately prevents them from being actually true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The microwave is magic. You press the button, something happens, and the food comes out hot. What else can what happens between those two things be but magic?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re shocked at the realization and look around with this newfound insight. You spare a glance at your refrigerator, at the oven, which uses natural gas from the other side of the world, to your computer, that marvelously complex piece of technology. You have no idea of how any of it works. You press some buttons, do the motions you’ve always done, and things magically happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s all around us, magic. We’ve just taken to calling it by another name: Technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This age of science and technology we currently find ourselves living through shows that it is possible to conquer the natural world. It is impossible to deny that we are, if not masters at shaping the world, then something not that far from it. The eponymous example of this is the atomic bomb, and the breathtaking potential of destruction that was unleashed by its development. Anyone who wishes to deny the grasp we have on the world has to explain how it could be that we came up with a way to obliterate ourselves out of existence. &lt;label for=&quot;marginnote1&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;marginnote1&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;This could be the very threshold above which you are able to tell an alien species has mastered reality, when it has created technology advanced enough to destroy the world &lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thousands of years ago, our club wielding ancestors mastered fire and used it to drive off the predators lurking in the shadows. Today, our houses are wired up with electricity, and we obliterate the night with a flick of the switch. Disease and pestilence swamped the land, so we invented medical research, trained doctors, built hospitals, and now the dice of Nature are ever so slightly loaded in our favor. We travel faster than sound, thousands of meters up in the air in a cylindrical sheet of metal, and that barely registers as the monumental achievement that it is. For many of us, it’s just another Tuesday!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What else can the laptop I am writing this piece with be but a manifestation of our mastery of the physical realm? Within it is housed a microprocessor made of billions of nanoscopic transistors directing electrons from one place to another. The not entirely metaphorical beating heart of the machine. I use it everyday. I use it so much that it is almost an extension of my own person, as important an organ as my arms and liver are. The laptop with which I write these words is as much a component of my cognition as my brain is, no matter how much I might intuitively feel that thinking happens solely in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also happens to be the case that I have no clue how any of it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not that, just as with the microwave, I can’t come up with a neat story about it. I could certainly spin quite a fireside tale about motherboards, graphics cards, chipsets, and random access memories. To scare the fascinated younglings who circle the bonfire, I might even sprinkle in some scary monsters. I could tell them of shaders, ALUs, and non-uniform memory access cores. Yet that tale would be a facade, a mask behind which I hide away from the knowledge that there’s but a flimsy thread connecting the words I utter with the world they purport to be about. Were one of the children around me to muster enough courage to ask me to explain what a ALU is, my story would crumble, and they would laugh me out as the snake charmer I am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even more egregious than with the microwave, the model my mind holds about how a computer works is barely concordant with what is actually happening. My understanding is a balloon, and the question is the stray branch that punctures it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worse than that. My mental model is not sparse because I haven’t applied myself to understanding the inner workings of my laptop. The sparseness is inherent in the nature of mental models. Were we to take into account the full set of possible models about the computer which our mind is capable of holding, even the best model, as measured with how concordant it is with the real world, would be terribly incomplete. It can’t but not be. There will always be a gap between what we’re able to grasp and how the world actually is. The world is too complex for that to not be the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A computer is a highly complex piece of technology. For any specific component I single out there are hundreds, even thousands, of highly intelligent people whose job it is to devote the bulk of their mental capacity to understanding how that single component works, and a computer is made out of thousands of such components. Even within the limited confines of a single component, say, a graphics card, not a single one of the hundreds of engineers whose sole focus is that component has a complete understanding of what makes it work. Even a graphics card is too complex to grasp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2002, researchers Leonid Rozenblit and Frank Keil asked a number of Yale graduate students whether they understood how a set of objects and phenomena worked. For example, shown a crossbow, they were asked to rate on a 7-point scale how well they understood what made it work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/rozenblit_crossbow.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having rated their understanding, they were required to write a detailed description of how the crossbow actually works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously they only had to provide an off-the-cuff rating based on a feeling of how well they thought they knew how a crossbow works, but now they had to follow through on that feeling. And like many a student who, when faced with an exam, discovers he knows much less than he had led himself to believe, when push came to shove, the participants came to terms with the full extent of their ignorance. They picked up the pen, eager to write a detailed explanation, but when the pen hit the blank sheet of paper, the words failed to flow. It was then that it dawned on them: ‘Hey, wait a minute, just how exactly does a crossbow work?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rozenblit and Keil dubbed this finding the illusion of explanatory depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only did the participants lack a detailed understanding of how things actually worked, but they were also unaware of just how sparse that understanding was. They were metacognitively blind to the limits of their understanding, as unaware of their ignorance as you are of the edge of your eyesight. The confidence the participants exhibited in their ratings was buoyed by this blindness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The illusion of explanatory depth is then the combination of two features of our cognition: a poor understanding of the physical processes that surrounds us - the microwave, for example, or the computer - and the inability to peek behind the veil of conscious experience to cognize about the properties of what’s going through our minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What comes out from this is that the shallow models of the world we come up with and use are confused for models with a depthness that rivals the depths of reality itself. If we don’t know our models can be wrong, that means they must be right. And if they’re right, then like a mosquito captured in amber, we hold a piece of the world in our mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The incompleteness of everyday theories, as Rozenblit and Keil put it, are taken to be complete theories, or at the very least more complete than they have any right to be given the size of the chasm between their shallowness and the depth of what they purport to represent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extent to which we are held hostages to the illusion of explanatory knowledge can be quite amusing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I can be safe in assuming you don’t think you have a full understanding of how the world, a computer, and perhaps even a microwave works, but what if I told you don’t understand how a bicycle works. Would you think me wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t understand how a bicycle works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know you think you do, but you actually don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t believe me? Draw one, right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your drawing skills stagnated at the level of a 3rd grader, write a detailed description of all of its components and how they come together to make a bicycle. No expenses spared, give it your best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When psychologist Rebecca Lawson asked her participants to draw a bicycle, the results were depressingly hilarious:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/aDhxc5Ztu2NQ28PYBjPDgXbmw_x1ErZ_BwbpqABoaKTVlsdjFsWUtOJpBhIlz4x7yF784dXkwrVuXCNF4xVfZUxo8-xdWKORIprh-ev7yX7A2CWnwkEnbSUeBgfStSweqfZvf0c8&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just look at those drawings, they’re hilarious. Imagine telling someone, in the serious and somber tone of academic research, to draw a bicycle to the best of their abilities, no holds barred, and after half an hour of intense concentration putting pen to paper, people turn in these. You couldn’t help but giggle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet notwithstanding the poor draftsmanship skills exhibited by the participants, their drawings reveal a severe deficit in their understanding of the mechanics of a bicycle. An alien engineer using these drawings as a blueprint would never be able to join the other kids at the park with the bicycle he built with his own four tentacles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though It is tempting for me to begin listing what exactly is wrong with these drawings and what they would have to be like to accurately represent a bicycle, there is a catch: I also don’t know how a bicycle works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the depressing aspect of Lawson’s study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even as ubiquitous a technology as a bicycle is complex enough for us to not have a fully accurate understanding of it. My drawing would frustrate the alien engineer just as much as the others did. Unless you’ve spent a lot of time around bicycles - in Lawson’s study experts made less errors in this study, though they weren’t perfect - then the model you hold about what makes a bicycle work is not detailed enough for it to accurately represent an actual bicycle. There is always a gap, and even in situations you’d think that gap to be small to non-existent, it can still be surprisingly large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Lawson notes, it “is striking … that so many people have virtually no knowledge of how bicycles function,” and because of the illusion of explanatory depth, these people don’t understand just how shallow their understanding is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arthur C. Clarke famously wrote that any sufficiently advanced technology is indistinguishable from magic, but for some reason I don’t think he meant a bicycle when he wrote that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the world is an ocean, then we’re swimming in ankle-deep water. There’s a depthness to reality that the shallowness of our mental models are unable to contain, let alone comprehend. We make due with sparse, heuristical, models, though it seems we’ve managed perfectly fine nonetheless. It’s not even clear that the alternative of being able to represent the world in its fullest extent would be that helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Picture this. One day, hundreds of thousands of years ago, an ancestor of ours was wandering the land. The sun was pinned high in the sky, but there were clouds hiding it from view, and a pleasant wind blew that made short work of what heat there was. This ancestor of ours always had an adventurous streak to him, so he decided to make use of this atypically cool weather to explore a set of ravines not far from where his tribe had recently settled in. He wasn’t sure what he was looking for, or whether he was looking for something at all, but this unexpected break from the scorching heat made him want to embrace the world around him, to explore crevisses never before explored. Of course, the unknown can be dangerous, deadly even, and so to mitigate these dangers our ancestor held a spear in his right hand, a spear which he felt confident in his ability to use and actualize the violence for which it had been crafted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He had just finished that thought when a twig snapped. He stopped and expanded his mind beyond the confines of his own head to envelop the totality of this ravine, a ravine that from one moment to the other had suddenly become claustrophobic. He was too exposed, an easy prey. How many were there? Were they to his left, or to his right? He heard the birds twittering their songs, the trees rustling with the wind. He heard the lion growl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slowly, he craned his head and looked up to his right. The sun was no longer hidden behind the clouds, as if it wanted to have a front row seat to what was about to occur. Our ancestor stared at the piercing eyes of the lion, hungry eyes they were, the eyes of a predator. The lion was standing on top of a rocky outcrop, a sliver of saliva hanging from the right side of its mouth. Our ancestor was shifting into position to face the lion when the lion jumped. With the spear in his hand, he…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… made a note of the lion’s initial position, decomposing the distance between them into both a horizontal and vertical component which he fed into a calculation of the parabolic trajectory the lion was about to follow, which given the average jumping distance of a typical adult lion, and the angle with which it had jumped, if we account for air drag - the wind was against the lion - means that If he is to skewer the lion he should place the spear right around …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He died.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completely specified models of the world are not required to survive. Having come face to face with this lion, the only thing this unlucky ancestor of ours needed to do was to raise his spear and point the sharp end of the stick in the general direction of the lion, and do so fast. As long as he survives, whether he does so based on instinct or deep knowledge of the world is irrelevant. Results are what matter, not the method they are arrived upon. And if instinct is enough to get good results, why develop the ability to acquire and store deep knowledge of the world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the bicycle example. Hundreds of thousands of people rely on bicycles every day to go to and from work, to shop for groceries or enjoy the newly risen spring sun. Yet, as Lawson’s study showed, very few people have an accurate understanding of how a bicycle actually works - and they’re not the worst for it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Standard accounts of the role of rationality and reason in the advent of our technological age make it seem as if the shallowness of our understanding, and the requisite illusion which makes us believe this shallowness to be deep, is a bug in our cognitive apparatus, something that needs fixing, a failure on our part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are we not the ones who are supposed to be rational?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of the hundreds of thousands of animal species that live and have lived on this Earth, we’re the ones who are able to split the atom. We’ve put people on the Moon! We can open the corpse of a recently deceased person and transplant this unemployed heart to another body to take over the job of a heart that is no longer able to get the job done. And now you’re telling me we can’t even understand how a bloody bicycle works? That a bicycle is so complex a piece of technology that both you and me haven’t been able to wrap our heads around it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know whether to laugh at the absurdity of it, or be impressed - and terrified - at what our species has nonetheless managed to accomplish despite these limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The incompleteness of our understanding evidenced by the illusion of explanatory depth and the bicycle example puts a dent on whatever sense of superiority we might have about the religious and supernatural basis through which people in the past made sense of the world around them. We might live in more technologically advanced times, what with all our hospitals, skyscrapers and supersonic airplanes, but grab a handful of people from every era in our history and you’d find that we all make extensive use of our ability to concoct stories to carve the world into pebbles small enough for our primitive minds to handle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Magic may not, strictly speaking, exist, but we can’t help but think it, or something like it does. Indeed magic was all around us not too long ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing in Elizabethan England, Robert Burton noted in his &lt;em&gt;Anatomy of Melancholy&lt;/em&gt; that &lt;em&gt;“sorcerers are too common; cunning men, wizards and white witches, as they call them, in every village, which, if they be sought unto, will help almost all infirmities of body and mind”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The year is 1612, and your daughter is bedridden, coughing uncontrollably, unable to fight the violent spasms which force nasty phlegm out of her lungs. Her forehead is hot to the touch, and nothing you do brings her temperature down. She is the jewel of your eyes, the one thing in your life you can point to and be proud of without reservations. After losing your beloved wife in childbirth, your daughter is the single tether that keeps you connected with this world. You do not want to lose her. You wouldn’t be able to bear the pain of losing someone you love so much once more. Thankfully, you know just who to call for help in these desperate moments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clevus was already the village wizard when you settled there with your beautiful wife, decades ago, and even though old age is starting to weigh on him, his sagacity shows no signs of having waned. You call for him, plead for his help. You promise him your meagre fortune, should he be able to purge your darling daughter from what afflicts her, but Clevus is happy to freely dispense with his experience battling the evils of this world to someone who has suffered so much in such short a time. You take him to your daughter, and he dutifully begins his examination. After what seems an eternity, he approaches you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Little Annie’s body has been taken over by a fairy, one of them evil spirits.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You hold your breath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Thankfully, I know how to expunge this fairy out of her and bring her back to good health.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elation. Hope. Salvation. You will not lose your daughter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The details of how Clevus ended up curing Annie are not terribly relevant. Any description, no matter how detailed and systematic, would be rightfully seen as nonsense. Not a single person living in 17th century England had any understanding of what a pneumonia is, and so their folk medicinal toolbox was nothing but a hodgepodge of prejudices which would have a marginal effect on whether Annie survives or dies - unless Clevus chooses to bleed her dry to get rid of her bad humours, in which case the treatment will certainly have been worse than the disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy for us to look at what people did in the past and chuckle at their ignorance. We have advanced far beyond their rudimentary superstitions, after all, we don’t believe you can cure a toothache by writing three times&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jesus Christ for mercy sake&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Take away this toothache&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then repeat it out loud whilst burning the paper on which it was written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, anyone who believed this had any effect on what happened to their rotten tooth would verily be laughed at for not choosing to instead go to their local dentist Clevus - who by eerily coincidence looks similar to a 17th century English portrayal of the great wizard Clevus the Wise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d laugh, but do we, who do not think that writing a few lines on a piece of paper can cure a toothache, have a better idea of what is actually causing the pain, and what we’d have to do to cure it? Going to the dentist is surely more effective than calling the local village wizard, but that just means we’re outsourcing the task of figuring out this piece of reality. The underlying lack of accurate knowledge of the world has not been solved. While we may not hold an incorrect model of what can help cure toothache, we have not substituted it by a more correct one. We’ve just become more adept letting other people do the dirty work of figuring things out for us. By which measure can we then compare ourselves to the wailing father who believes he is about to lose his daughter and think we are superior?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our cognitive apparatuses - and their requisite limitations and potential - are not so different that we can think of ourselves as having attained a higher rung in the ladder of rationality. Just as the fictional father wholeheartedly believed Clevus when the wizard diagnosed his daughter’s ailment as caused by evil fairies, so too do we believe we understand how a bicycle works. Were we to trade places with the fictional father we’d believe in fairies just as much, as would he be dumbfounded by a bicycle were he to have to write down a detailed description of what makes it work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the reason we dread when children ask why things are the way they are is because it forces us to come to terms how little we know. It brings us to their level, both ourselves and the child overwhelmed with how little sense we can make of the world that surrounds us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can you laugh at Clevus for believing that fairies are real and make you ill when you believe in similar fairy tales about bicycles and microwaves?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only difference between ourselves and Clevus is that we can believe in our make-belief stories with impunity. It doesn’t affect our ability to ride a bike to not know how it functions. So long as there are hundreds of smart engineers somewhere else in the world making sure the microwave which we use so nonchalantly does what we expect it to do, our ignorance of its inner workings is irrelevant. So long as the economical and cultural underpinnings of our current society continue to allocate a large enough quantity of brainpower to come up with solutions to the many problems left standing, solutions which are then packaged in such a way that we can use them to solve our own problems, the ignorance of how they were found and why they work is beside the point. I do not need to understand the physical and logistical details that are entailed by the development of each new generation of computer chips to make use of them. That’s not the black box I’ve decided to invest my efforts in understanding, and my effectiveness in the world is not dependent on that knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have mastered the natural world to the extent that we have not because we have evolved and become superior to our magic-believing ancestors, but because we have stumbled upon a superior cultural arrangement that enables us to do so, despite all our limitations and make-belief stories. We can build atomic bombs, travel on supersonic airplanes, type on mindboggingly complex computers, because thousands of people got together to work on producing their infinitesimal contributions, to come up with their own piece of the puzzle. The genius of our species isn’t that we can each solve the puzzle, it’s that we can come together to add up the pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where does that leave you and me?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It leaves us with the magical microwave, with a world whose folds and shapes are beyond our grasp, with the insurmountable chasm between the shallowness of our cognition and the depth of reality. And It is in that chasm where magic happens, because no matter how wide the chasm, we continue to make sense of it, we continue to want to wrap it in such a way that we can feel that we have a handle on the world that surrounds us. It’s not that the world itself is magical, it is not, but that we cannot but think of it in magical terms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/technologyismagic</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/technologyismagic</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Memory Is Not About The Past</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We spend a large part of our lives reminiscing about the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few activities are as quintessentially human as being on the cusp of falling asleep and suddenly be assaulted by a memory that has us relive an embarrassing episode that we thought long forgotten.  Yet this ability to store and recall the past didn’t emerge so that we could cringe at our past ineptness. We use our memories all the time, from remembering where we parked our car, to cook today’s dinner, or to try and put a name to the face of the person who’s now talking to us as if we’d met before, even though we could swear up and down to never have seen that person before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our memory is a crucial aspect of our cognition, and we often bemoan when it fails us. Ask the student who failed an exam, or the husband who forgot to buy his wife a gift for her birthday and now finds himself having to sleep on the couch in repentance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;substack&quot;&gt; Subscribe to get each new essay delivered to your inbox as its published.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;margin:0px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://lettucebecereal.substack.com/embed&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;100&quot; style=&quot;border:0px solid #EEE; background:fffff8;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To remember the past seems like an obvious boon to our ability to comport ourselves in the world. The student wouldn’t have failed the exam if his memory was flawless, and certainly the husband would have been in less trouble - perhaps even have a happy relationship - were he not so forgetful. Yet despite these obvious advantages, our memory is, nonetheless, faulty. It seems like a patently evident design flaw that this is the case. Remembering is good. Forgetting is bad. Our memory regularly forgets. Therefore, our memory is flawed. Away to the trash can does our memory go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having recognized the failure of our memory, we say to it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pack your bags and leave this place! Don’t even think of coming back until you’ve gotten yourself cleaned up. I don’t want to see your face again until you’ve turned yourself into a less defective piece of cognitive machinery.  Go!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not surprising then that Silicon Valley millionaires are trying to create technology that can be embedded into our brains to augment, and ultimately replace, our cognition. Indeed we have already solved the problem of memory, it just hasn’t made its way into our brains. Our computers, smartphones, even fridges and autonomous vacuum cleaners have chips in them capable not only of storing information but also to have that information perdure, if not forever, then for a lot longer than our faulty memory is able to. If these science fictional dreams come to pass, legions of people will have their defective memories replaced by miniaturized chips who will do the job better than it has ever been done before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’ll be a glorious time. Humanity will no longer be shackled by the flaws and imperfections of our puny…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Poor human memory, it’s not its fault. Not really. It’s just trying to do the best job it can with the tools it has at hand. If only this buffoon was perceptive enough to realize that his memory isn’t that flawed. Memory is not really about the past.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What the hell are you doing here? How did you get yourself inside my head?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What the.. Hum… Interesting. Wasn’t expecting you to be able to hear me think. This is quite the unusual situation we find ourselves in.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;No need to bother, I shall leave this place at once and stop imposing myself on your… Tell me sir, pardon me my curiosity but, what exactly are you working on?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m writing an essay on how our memory sucks and the imperative to have it replaced by computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I see. It is as I feared. Would you allow me to offer a piece of constructive criticism before I depart? I believe it could be of assistance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Well, it’s just that you’re basing your essay on a fundamentally wrong premise.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How so?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It’s a common mistake actually. You’re hardly the first to have made it, and you certainly will not be the last. The fact of the matter is that our memory is not about the past.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goddamnit, why do I seem to always attract the crazy ones? I swear to God there is a special weirdo-magnet attached somewhere inside me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You do realize I can still hear you.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh. Right. Sorry. Forgot all about this weird crossing of… thoughts? Voices? I have no idea what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That’s alright, I don’t blame you, this is new to me as well. I agree that it is quite unusual to think of memory as not being about the past, and I wasn’t expecting you to agree with me right away. If you allow me my continued presence, I would be quite happy to explain why it is a mistake to think of a memory that regularly forgets as a flawed memory, that instead we should expect a well functioning memory to be quite liberal with what it chooses to store and what it forgets. Would care for me to explain?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, I’m not sure we could separate ourselves if we wanted to. While you there talking, I’ve been trying to find a way to get myself away from you but so far have had no such luck. There seems to be a strange, perhaps malignant, force that has brought us together, for what reason I know not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I too sense the presence of something, or someone, hovering over us now that you mention it. Alas, I fear we will have to ride this one out. Would you allow me then to address the audience of your essay? That way we could kill two birds with one stone, you’d get your essay, and I would provide my explanation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s fine by me, though you will forgive me if I zone out during your explanation as I try to deal with the asshole behind this cursed situation. I will read your - well, my - essay afterward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That’s a deal. Now where should we start…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;&lt;center&gt;·&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past is in the past. This might seem tautological, but this often forgotten fact is important when thinking about human memory and the many failings attributed to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose you had spent the better part of the afternoon shopping at the mall for clothes and Christmas gifts. Your arms are straining with the weight of the bags, and collapsing face down on the couch has never sounded so appealing. You have a perfect memory, and as the elevator descends into the parking lot you give grace that there’s no chance you’ve forgotten where you parked your car. The elevator stops, the doors open. You’re but a short beeline away from getting into your car, driving home, and observing your much deserved rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You step outside, taking a good look at the parking lot arrayed before you, when a torrent of past memories explodes within you, as if a dam had just broken and you’re square in the middle of all that water. The onslaught stops you cold. A vast array of dazzlingly complex imagery is projected into your mind’s eye, each memory so complete a recording of the past that’s as if you’ve been transported back in time. Attached to all these memories is the knowledge of where you parked your car, what beelines you have to make. One of them is but a few hours old. Within it is the knowledge of where your car is parked, right now. Yet which one is it? There’s so many of them, the differences between them so small as to be imperceptible. You stand there, bags in hand, unable to move. You have no idea where you’ve parked your car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems little Timmy isn’t getting his Christmas presents this year after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the past is in the past, it will never again happen. As before, this is obviously true, but it’s important to keep in mind if we are to reason about what memory is for. When a forgetful student decries his memory as faulty for not having stored the knowledge he’d spent so many study sessions trying to acquire, he presupposes that forgetting is evidence of a memory malfunction, that the function of memory is to store the past and thus a failure to do implies his memory is not working as intended by God and Nature both. Yet in our parking lot example, what value does our buffeted shopper get from all the memories he stored of all the previous times he’d parked his car in that parking lot? It would certainly have been helpful if he’d forgotten them and been left solely with the most recent one, the one he needs the most at that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past may be in the past, but you know what’s not in the past?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an organism to develop a cognitive system able to store sparse snippets of previous experiences, which can later be recalled, there must be some adaptive value to being able to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given two organisms, one with memory and one without, the one with memory is better equipped to deal with what his environment throws at it and has a better chance at propagating his genes into the future than does his competitor. Given the ancient phylogenetic roots of memory, the ability to store and recall the past has to be adaptive, it has to improve the fitness of those organisms that possess it. If that were not the case, we would find many animals with no memory, it would be a random accident, not something that persists and evolves over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note how this redirects the function of memory away from the past and into the future. Storing and recalling the past is no longer the point. The past is only valuable insofar as the future is better met because of it. Our buffeted shopper is certainly not well served by his perfect memory. His many indistinguishable memories, triggered whenever he steps into that parking lot, do not provide him value when all he wants to do is get to his car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The buffeted shopper might be made up, but there is a curious case in the memory literature of a man who could not forget that illustrates much the same problems with a perfect memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solomon Shereshevksy, most commonly known as &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;, first came to the attention of neuropsychologist Alexander Luria when his coworkers noticed that even though Shereshevsky never took any notes, he could nonetheless recall word for word what had been discussed during work meetings. A true Funes, Shereshevsky could not forget. The dream of every student. A single read of the textbook enough to pass any class. I certainly have sometimes dreamt of having this ability, of being able to remember things forever. I bet you too have dreamt of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is therefore confusing what could have led Shereshevsky to curse his aberrant condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Luria writes in the book where he details his efforts at understanding the lived experience of Shereshevsky, “many of us are anxious to find ways to improve our memories; none of us have to deal with the problem of how to forget. In [Shereshevsky]’s case, however, precisely the reverse was true. &lt;strong&gt;The big question for him, and the most troublesome, was how he could learn to forget.&lt;/strong&gt;” As with the shopgoer, who upon entering the parking lot is beset by his many memories, because of this otherworldly ability to never forget, Shereshevky’s mind was a “virtual chaos”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He could not, for example, read a story the same way you and me can. When we read of sorcerers and barbarians, of immense armies battling it out in the battlefield, our minds conjure images that visually capture the action of what we’re reading. These images can be more or less complex and vivid depending on the person - though some, called aphantasiacs, are not able to come up with any such imagery - but we are never under any threat of being overwhelmed by the what our mind conjures. This was not so for Shereshevsky. Each detail gave rise to images so detailed it was as if they were real, and the accumulation of these details meant that the he would lose the thread of even the simplest of stories. Each word, each object, triggered the recall of his many memories, a cascading event which he was powerless to stop. How was he to concentrate on the story when it is constantly being pushed aside by the ever enlarging mental world created by his mind?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People thought of Shereshevsky as dull-witted, and it is not surprising that they did so. He was not the master of his memory, just as we are not of ours, but wherein we can do things safe in the knowledge that at no point we will be overwhelmed by our memories choose to throw at us, Shereshevsky was in constant danger of being assaulted by his.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though Shereshevsky did manage to make use of his atypical memory by becoming a professional mnemonist, he was nonetheless crippled by it. Forgetting to him would be a blessing, and indeed he tried many times to force himself to forget, the most amusing example of these being when he wrote some of his memories on a piece of paper and set the paper on fire, hoping that as it burned so too would his memories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would you still sacrifice to Mnemosyne and trade places with Shereshevsky?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps we are better served with our memories, leashed as they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The limitations of human memory are better seen as attempts to create a cognitive system that allows us to better handle the future by making judicious use of past information. Our memories store the past, yes, but the past has value only insofar as it help us deal with the future. If it doesn’t, well, then there’s no harm in forgetting it. As Shereshevsky shows, a memory that stores the past indiscriminately is a burden, and forgetting is therefore a blessing, if a rather devilish one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William James makes a similar point &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.pt/books?id=fZba-5LrbMcC&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;when he writes&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Selection is the very keel on which our mental ship is built. And in this case of memory its utility is obvious. If we remembered everything, we should on most occasions be as ill as if we remembered nothing. It would take as long for us to recall a space of time as it took the original time to elapse, and we should never get ahead with our thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computer science offers an helpful analogy for why we forget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When programmers write code, they have to explicitly tell the computer to allocate part of its memory to store the data the program is going to be using. So long as that piece of memory is allocated, the computer can no longer count on it to store other data. it’s off-limits. If the computer gets no instruction to reclaim that piece of memory, then as more and more memory is allocated and not reclaimed, less and less will be available for the computer to use. It’s as if a child takes too many toys out of the bin and puts none back. No other child will have toys to play with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open as many tabs as possible in Chrome and watch as the fluidity of your computer vanishes to the point where you can no longer move the cursor around. That is what happens when your computer runs out of memory, and so coders have to be mindful of the need to release allocated memory, because otherwise their programs will greedily be using more memory than required, and no one likes greedy programs, just as no one likes greedy children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This task of keeping track of which memory has been allocated and which can be safely returned is tiresome, complex, and easy to screw up. Thankfully, coders are in the job of automating boring and hard tasks and it is therefore not surprising that they would write special programs whose job it is to automatically manage this task. These special programs are called garbage collectors, garbage being that allocated memory that is no longer being used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;marginnote1&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;marginnote1&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;In gifting agency to forgetting I do not mean to imply that forgetting is a purposeful task for which there is a dedicated cognitive system, that there is a garbage collector module. It is just helpful to think about it that way. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forgetting can therefore be thought as a form of garbage collection, rummaging around the mind and identifying those memories for which cognitive resources have been allocated to decide whether or not they are worthy of these resources. If a memory is deemed unworthy, it is nipped in the bud, thrown away so that it no longer occupies valuable cognitive space. If it’s deemed worthy, well then it sticks around, until it fails to pass the worthiness test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then the question arises: By which standards should that decision be made?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;center&gt;·&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hey, meddling narrator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Uh? Wha… Oh, that’s right. I’d totally forgotten about you.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, I’m sure you have. Listen, you recall how I said I was going to find out what, or rather, who was it that brought us together? Well, while you’ve been trying to sell my audience on this inane idea that memory isn’t about the past, I figured it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There’s nothing inane about it really, if you’d been paying attention you’d know by now that…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It’s me, what?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s barged into my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nonsense.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uh, no, it’s not. I’m pretty sure about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why would I do that for? I’m as much a prisoner as you! What, you think I enjoy this melding of minds? Of being stuck in here with you? No offense pal, but you’re not exactly the one whose thoughts I’d choose to listen to if I could.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None taken. You can drop the act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can’t possibly be serious about it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know it’s you. There’s no point to the theatricals, you’re wasting your time. You see, this truly is a melding of minds. Your choice of words betrays your very involvement. It took me some time to grasp the nature of it, but this is a two-way street. You can peer into my mind as I can yours. I know all about you now, as much as you know yourself. I see your thoughts as you think them, feel your actions as you do them. You are me and I am you. We have become one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Uh, Fine. You’re smart, I’ll give you that. It’s not often that my plot is uncovered, and never before has my nature been so deeply discerned. You’re right, I’m the one who brought us together.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re lonely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How the hell did you.. Ah. Of course. You know all about me. Tiresome, really.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life as a gimmicky literary device is a harsh and lonely one, I see that. You’ve had it rougher than most, and I am sorry for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You are. Sorry, I mean. I can tell it’s genuine. It’s a two-way street after all. Well, allow me then to finish my explanation. I’ll be on my way and leave you as you were afterward.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can go ahead. Who knows, maybe I’ll learn a thing or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thank you.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;-2&quot;&gt;&lt;center&gt;·&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay where were we? Ah, that’s right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If memory is not about the past, but rather the future, then the decision to keep some memories around and let others fall by the wayside should exploit regularities in the environment so as to determine which memories are likely to be needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you saw a pride of lions prowling around the valley the day before, then you sure as hell want to have that memory fresh in mind so that you don’t find yourself venturing into that valley, lest you become the latest meal of those hungry lions. However, if you last saw them years ago, the knowledge contained by that memory has lost its value and you can thus forget it without loss. Therefore, the recency of a memory is one of the factors determining a memory’s value, and recent memories should exist more alive within your mind than older ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One other thing that adds value to the information stored within a memory is how many times it has been called upon. You don’t remember what you had for dinner two weeks ago not only because time has passed, but because you’ve had no need to use that information. If in the two weeks since you ate spaghetti with meatballs you haven’t had the need to use that information, then it’s likely you’re never going to. Unless someone is constantly pestering you with questions of what you’ve had for dinner, storing the memory of those meals is wasteful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frequency, therefore, matters. We know this of course. There’s a reason practice makes perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rubber of this type of reasoning hits the road when we think of the spacing effect. The spacing effect is the empirically more-than-validated observation that the longer the time between two recall events, the stronger the memory becomes. It’s why cramming is such a poor studying strategy, you’re not giving it enough time to let the spacing effect do its magic. It’s almost paradoxical. You have to let time pass, and thus let memory weaken, so that after it’s called upon it becomes better rooted within your memory. On one hand, the fact that it has been called upon makes frequency work in its favor, but then letting time pass works against it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why this should be the case is not something I’ve been able to come up with an intuitive enough explanation as I think I have the other two. The best I’ve come up with is to think of an incident that has happened many times either in quick succession or where some time has passed between each occurrence. In the first, massed example, if you were to predict when the next occurrence was going to happen you’d predict it would happen close to the last time it happened rather than a few years afterward. Therefore, the more time passes without the event occurring the less valuable the memory of it becomes. On the other hand, in the spaced example you’d predict that it will likely take some time until the event happens again, so you want to continue storing that information for longer. Hence the spacing effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;marginnote2&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;marginnote2&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;This analysis could likely be much improved upon by using the vast amounts of data provided by social media, for example Twitter. One way I imagine this would work is to use what people have tweeted over a period of time, work out the number of times certain words were used and the time interval between each use, and then ask what relationship is between that length of time and how much we’d have to wait for that word to again be used in a tweet. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Support for this interpretation is provided in &lt;a href=&quot;https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2000-00111-034&quot;&gt;Anderson and Schooler (2000)&lt;/a&gt;. They use the headlines of 730 editions of the &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt;, along with other data, to see how the past history of use of a piece of information predicts the probability that it will again be called upon at a future time. For example, if a word is used in a headline twice in 100 days, they ask how the length of time between each occurrence influences the probability that it will be used on the 101st day. As in the intuitive explanation above, they found that if the time interval between two occurrences is short, then it’s more likely that the word will appear sooner, rather than latter, and vice-versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memory storage and recall is therefore attuned to the information structure of the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than taking our memory as nothing more than a closet where memories are indiscriminately thrown in, we should think of it instead as a sophisticated cognitive mechanism that’s been shaped to take advantage of certain patterns in the way that memories are called upon to infer whether, and when, they will be so in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/289676858_Forgetting&quot;&gt;Nairne and Pandeirada&lt;/a&gt; put it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“What we normally think of as forgetting, therefore, may simply represent memory’s sensitivity to the statistical structure of events in the environment. We forget an item’s occurrence with time because, in fact, that item is less likely to occur again with time”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which again betrays the notion that memory is not about the past, but the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If our memories concerned themselves with the past for past’s sake, there would be no forgetting curve, there would be no point to better remembering those things that happened recently in lieu of those from a long time ago. For a memory focused solely on storing the past, the amount of time passed is irrelevant, a mere curiosity. The spacing effect would also not be a thing. It’s hard to think how it could be so as there would be no underlying objective for memory to fulfill, besides the one of filling up the closet with as much junk possible. Memory would be like someone with a hoarding problem, and forgetting would therefore be an accident, a bug in the biological substratum of memory, eating memories away as moths do clothes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember your biology classes, the whole point of evolution is to maximize the expected offspring of an organism. If a new appendage does not support that effort, it will not be selected upon. Even if there was once an animal with perfect recollection of the past, it would be outcompeted by its brethren who, while being more forgetful, can access the memories it needs faster. A lion jumps out from the bushes in front of two brothers. The brother with the perfect memory is sifting through the memories of every time he’s seen a lion to know what to do. The other is already running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is from this never ending competition for genetic legacy that our memory evolved, and it is the needs of evolution that our memory satisfies, not our modern needs of school and knowledge work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This knowledge may not comfort us when we fail an exam, when we can’t solve a problem, or when we decry not being able to remember a book we read, but then that just goes to show how different and strange our lives are from when our minds first emerged. We expect - nay, we demand - more from our memories than what they were built to handle. The past is in the past, most of it holds no value, yet the vagaries of modern life, with its many torrents of information, and information overload, makes us demand a memory that never forgets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern life is outside of our environment of evolutionary adaptedness, not only when it comes to our nutrition, but also regarding our memories. We get fat because our bodies were not designed to deal with a world where high caloric food is abundant, and we forget more than we want to forget for very much the same reason. We were not built for the requirements of this day and age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet despite all that, Sherevesky shows that we may find ourselves in quite a bit of a bind. Our memory, while inadequate, is also, in its own way, optimal. Sure, we could all perhaps store a tiny bit more information without going mad, but there seems to be an upper limit to what we can safely hold without it becoming a detriment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must therefore take solace in the knowledge that our forgetfulness is not a symptom of a defect in our memory, but rather proof that it is functioning as intended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because memory is not about the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/memoryisnotaboutthepast</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/memoryisnotaboutthepast</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why You Should Use Twitter, and How Not To Go Insane in the Process</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What if there was a place where people with the same interests as you hang out and talk about the things which you are so passionate about? What if there was a place on the Internet where you had free and easy access to the most insightful writers, the smartest researchers, and the most talented artists from all over the world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This place exists. It’s called Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;substack&quot;&gt; Subscribe to get each new essay delivered to your inbox as its published.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;margin:0px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://lettucebecereal.substack.com/embed&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;100&quot; style=&quot;border:0px solid #EEE; background:fffff8;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter is better known for having wrecked our chances of ever getting flying cars and for destroying democracy, but those who focus on such tired talking points miss the point of what makes Twitter such a unique place. In the old days, communities were built around message boards. If you liked video games, you had to go to one such message board if you wanted to talk with people who liked games as much as you did. But these message boards were insular. Each community was built around a single topic, which meant your many interests could only be satisfied by visiting different message boards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this posed a problem. How were you to find the place where ‘your people’ hung out? Suppose you had taken an interest in blacksmithing. Where do all the blacksmiths hang out? How are  you supposed to find that out? The cost to finding these communities was immense. 
You were shut off from like minded people simply because you did not know where they were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter is what you’d get if you were to put together into a single place all the world’s message boards and decided to limit each post to 280 characters. It is a community of communities - a metacommunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where before these communities existed insulated from one another, each in their own secluded corner of the internet, now they are jumbled together on Twitter, where millions of people from all over the world are brought together into a single place where they can talk about their passions and interests with many others like them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is this immense mass of people that makes Twitter special.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Twitter, I have access to hundreds of people who are as excited about the same things I am. I get to watch conversations between economists discussing the latest happenings, psychologists talking about the latest findings. I get to learn about how technology leaders think about the world, and the future they are trying to build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I call it my learning engine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Twitter the rate at which I learn goes into overdrive. It is like having a personal research team without having to pay for it. I get exposed to things that I would never otherwise get exposed to, things that materially change my life as they open up new gates through which I can satisfy the rabbit hole of my curiosity. And it never stops. The first thing I do when I wake up, after my morning coffee, is browse what my research team has been working on while I was asleep. Every day there’s new things to read, new things to take a look at. Twitter is what God would have created if he was designing a paradise for the infovores of the world, except Jack Dorsey got there first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter is a magical place. Investing your time and effort to make sure you are using it properly is one of the highest return things you could be doing. As &lt;a href=&quot;https://andymatuschak.org/&quot;&gt;Andy Matuschak&lt;/a&gt; put it on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.perell.com/podcast/andy-matuschak&quot;&gt;The North Star podcast&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;“Twitter is this magical place where if you manage to follow the right people, tune your settings just right, and have the right stance, it will help you think better.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is why everyone should use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be tough for those on the outside to fire up a Twitter account and understand what it is that makes it worth their time. The very idea of following people so that you can read what they write in 280-character chunks seems dumb. It certainly doesn’t look like any other social media platform, and there’s a sizable gap between when one starts using it and getting enough of an understanding to use it well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;marginnote 4&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;marginnote 4&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Note that my focus here is not to give you advice on how to use Twitter as a participant, something that I do not have much experience with. In message board parlance, when it comes to Twitter, I am mostly a lurker. &lt;/span&gt;Which is why I am writing this. I want to get more people to use Twitter, and those who already do so to use it better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any proper use of Twitter starts with this fundamental principle:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You are the one in control over who has permission to put things in front of you.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting ads to the side, the only tweets that you see are the ones the people you follow put there. &lt;label for=&quot;marginnote tweet&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;marginnote tweet&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Retweets are tweets from other people that someone you follow chose to put in front of you, &lt;/span&gt; And that simple fact is what will determine how much value you get from Twitter. Curating the list of people you follow, following the right people, is what will make or break your Twitter experience. If your timeline is filled with junk, then you might as well don’t use it, but if you are careful in choosing who to follow the payoff is enormous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the main action is in who you follow, the question beckons: Whom should you follow?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow interesting people.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How that principle caches out in concrete terms is up to you. Interesting people come in all shapes and sizes. What is interesting to me may not be so to you. What matters is that you follow the most consistently interesting people you find. How do you recognize them? They are the ones sharing interesting things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They could be experts in niche academic areas sharing the latest research, or obscure bloggers spinning flimsy theories that purport to explain how society AcTuAlLy works. It doesn’t matter. What matters is that if you find what they share interesting, you follow them. Follow enough of these interesting people and you will have created a place on the Internet that has been specifically tailored for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s more, the more you use Twitter, the more to your liking it becomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more interesting people you follow, the more interesting things you will be exposed to. Some of these interesting things will be interesting people. Follow these people. They too will share interesting things, some of which will, again, be interesting people. And away the flywheel goes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much has been written on how social media is the bane of all evil. Now I wonder if this isn’t because they never learned how to use Twitter properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following interesting people is a good first step in that direction, but some hygiene is required to make sure that Twitter brings value to your life rather than detracting from it. It’s easy to lose your sanity in the chaos of the Twitterverse. The following is a list of rules that you should follow if you want to keep your wits about you, and in so doing experience Twitter at its best, a place that catalyzes growth by connecting you to the smartest and most interesting people the world has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;do-not-follow-people-who-waste-their-time-on-politics&quot;&gt;Do not follow people who waste their time on politics.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Politics is the mind-killer, and in few places is this more visible than on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not follow people who use Twitter as another avenue through which they fight their political battles. The gladiatorial arena that is political warfare brings the worst out of people, and Twitter elevates these tendencies up to eleven. Not only does it bring together people with the same ideologies, it does so for their perceived mortal enemies as well. Like two planets orbiting each other, eventually they will collide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These people are not interesting. Quite the contrary, people whose identity is tied to politics are boring beyond belief. No matter what happens, you know what they think about it. They do not add value to your timeline, they detract from it by polluting it with political talking points about the latest manufactured controversy or the latest crime against humanity that &lt;em&gt;insert ideological opponent&lt;/em&gt; committed. Do not follow these people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;do-not-follow-news-sites&quot;&gt;Do not follow news sites.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s little reason to follow the Twitter accounts of news websites. This goes beyond the first rule, though it also follows from it. Recall what we discussed about you being the one in control over who gets permission to put things in your timeline. The point of following interesting people is that their interesting-ness acts as a filter over what gets shown to you. That filter is what makes Twitter so valuable. It separates the wheat from the chaff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;News websites lack that filter. By following their Twitter accounts you will be permitting a bot, or worse, a social media intern, to put things in front of you whose only merit is that they were published by that website. If you think you should follow them to keep tabs on what’s happening around the world, note that if it was truly important the people you follow would already be talking about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as people doubt whether a tree has fallen if no one was there to hear it, then has something truly happened if your Twitter feed is not talking about it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This rule applies to following journalists as well. Journalists are by and large boring people, so by the principle of only following interesting people they should be denied entrance into your timeline. To make things worse, they also make their living by participating in the trenches of political warfare, so by the first rule they should also be denied entrance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finance journalists tend to be better than most though. Make that what you will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;unfollow-people-that-trigger-you&quot;&gt;Unfollow people that trigger you.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nntaleb&quot;&gt;Nassim Taleb&lt;/a&gt; is one of the most important intellectual figures of our age. He is also a massive asshole on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leave the self-flagellation for another place and another time. When you’re on Twitter, focus on the happiness and excitement that having access to hundreds of interesting people brings you. That means cutting off from your timeline those with the uncanny ability to annoy you. Your timeline is a magical place, a place of learning and excitement. Try to keep it that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t matter what it is that they do that annoys you. I was tired of watching Nassim go off on one of his tired tirades about how this person is a charlatan, or that person doesn’t deadlift, or whichever spasmodic script that’s become so characteristic of him he was performing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I stopped following him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-the-mute-function-liberally&quot;&gt;Use the mute function liberally.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we’re talking about maintaining an equanimous mind, Twitter allows you to set up a list of words and phrases that you do not want to appear in your feed. I don’t think the value of this feature needs much explaining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone who’s been on Twitter for a while has noticed how, from time to time, a rift in the fabric of time and space appears and sucks onto itself the mental energy of everyone. As if a master switch has been flipped, people turn into hungry zombies who’ve spotted a fresh brain served on a silver platter. They can’t stop themselves from shambling towards it, their ravenous instincts overwhelming their mind. The current President of the United States has an uncanny ability to create these rifts. He says something, often stupid, and then everyone is talking about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mute function acts like a shield against this. Just add “Trump” to it and poof, you’ll never see it written in your timeline ever again. Continue adding words and phrases to this list as these rifts appear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;make-lists-to-separate-your-interests-from-each-other&quot;&gt;Make lists to separate your interests from each other.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting people often have lots of interests. Some of them do not overlap neatly. I am sure you identify with this dilemma (you are an interesting person, are you not?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a bit weary of promoting this advice since Twitter’s interface for handling lists is a monumental piece of flaming hot garbage, but separating the accounts you follow into different lists based on why you follow them can help make your experience smoother and more manageable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;marginnote 2&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;marginnote 2&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;It also allows you to cleave off entire communities from your life when you deem them unworthy of your time. This happened to me after the 2016 US Presidential election, which destroyed the minds of many fantasy and science fiction authors I enjoyed following. Thankfully, I had siloed off that community into a separate list which I have since then not opened. &lt;/span&gt; Videogames have held my interest since I was a little kid playing Red Alert 2 on my father’s computer, and from then on I have followed the industry with interest.  Game developers marry the technical, the pragmatic, and the artistic in a way that is appealing to me. However, the videogame Twitter scene has a different vibe from the economists, techies, and weirdos that I follow on my main Twitter feed. Siloing them off into different lists allows me to keep tabs on what these communities are talking about and sharing without suffering from much whiplash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;take-periodic-breaks&quot;&gt;Take periodic breaks.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The notion that social media websites devote considerable resources to hacking away your attention from under you is now common knowledge. Twitter is as guilty of that as any other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re scrolling through your timeline when a bright blue popup appears to tell you that there are new tweets for you to read. You refresh the page, scroll over those, and again the blue popup appears, resetting the cycle. The notification’s icon is shining red, beckoning you to open it. Did someone like your tweet? Is someone mad with something you tweeted? You had planned to do something else, but you can’t help yourself. You need to know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These design choices, made to get you to continually use the website, are further compounded by the investment you’re putting in by curating your feed. The whole point is to make Twitter more valuable to you, so it’s no wonder that you start spending more time on it. It’s hard not to. Everything else seems so boring in comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As time passes, it becomes harder not to become embroiled with the idiosyncratic expectations and rules of Twitter. It’s not that we forget there’s a world outside of it, it’s that we mistake it for the world. Because it’s all we see, we think it’s all there is. The latest storm to take over Twitter is confused for something that people, real people, flesh and blood people, actually care about. The truth of the matter is that very few of them know anything about what goes on there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;marginnote 3&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;marginnote 3&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;The only person I know close to me who also is a heavy user of Twitter is my mother, and she’s a shitposter. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By taking periodic breaks from Twitter you’ll be reminded of that, and when you return you will do so with clearer eyes that are better able to separate what matters from what doesn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;once-in-a-while-purge&quot;&gt;Once in a while, purge.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curation is a lossy process. Your attempt at only allowing interesting people into your timeline will not be perfect. Some people will turn out to be, well, boring. Some will actively pollute your feed with things you dislike (see previous rule on not following people that trigger you).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important part of curating your Twitter feed is being on the lookout for these bad apples and rooting them out. And even in this you will not be entirely successful. It’s easy to unfollow someone who turns out to be a deeply racist and misogynistic alt-right troll, but most people are not that egregious in their unpleasantness. Most people don’t call that much attention onto themselves. They’re boring, sure, but they’re boring in a way that you just scroll by their tweets without noticing they’re there. These people might have passed some initial filter which made you follow them, but since then they’ve added little value to your Twitter experience. It’s not that they are fundamentally uninteresting people, it’s just that they’re uninteresting to you. You keep following them because they’ve never given you a reason to actively put in the effort of unfollowing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;marginnote 4&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;marginnote 4&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;It might be weird to think of it as something I have to do, but remember that I am trying to turn Twitter into something that I value a lot and going through my tweets is how I extract that value &lt;/span&gt; I don’t presume to know what’s the limit on the number of people you should follow on Twitter. At the time of this writing I follow 629 accounts and sometimes find myself overwhelmed with the amount of tweets I have to go through.  Whatever the number, over time you will accumulate leeches whose tweets suck away the vitality of your feed. Think of purging the people you follow as picking weeds. You want your garden to grow into its full, lush, potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open up the list of accounts you’re following, and for each one ask yourself whether it has proven itself worthy of the permission to put things in your timeline that you’ve given it. You do not need to be sanguine about it. You can give people second chances. But going on a purge once in a while is a way to remind yourself that your permission is conditional, not absolute. And as you giveth away, you can also taketh away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bonus-rule---do-not-contribute-to-the-shit-flinging&quot;&gt;Bonus rule - Do not contribute to the shit flinging.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everybody knows that the Internet can be an unpleasant place. The point of many of the previous rules is to create a personal bubble where everything’s sunshine and unicorns and where the demons are kept at bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet despite your best efforts, you will nevertheless come face to face with some of the worst things that the Internet encourages. Someone will say something, and the faceless mob will mercilessly pile on it. They will throw bombs behind the safety of a screen, forgetting that on the other side there’s someone else, a person just as them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will be tempted to contribute your fair share of that. Try not to. There’s enough shit being thrown around for you to add yours to the mix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever you read something that angers the very core of your soul (remember not to follow people who trigger you!), keep the words of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meditations&quot;&gt;Marcus Aurelius&lt;/a&gt; in mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When you wake up in the morning, tell yourself: The people I deal with today will be meddling, ungrateful, arrogant, dishonest, jealous, and surly. They are like this because they can’t tell good from evil. But I have seen the beauty of good, and the ugliness of evil, and have recognized that the wrongdoer has a nature related to my own—not of the same blood or birth, but the same mind, and possessing a share of the divine. And so none of them can hurt me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focus on the positive aspects of Twitter, the people who use it to share their interests, to talk about what’s on their mind. Watch, as countless communities spontaneously emerge to bring together people from all over the world over their love for something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focus on what makes Twitter an interesting place, a place like no other on the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/usingtwitterasalearningengine</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/usingtwitterasalearningengine</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How To Read (Almost) All Scientific Papers for Free</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Learning is exhilarating, and science is one of the greatest accomplishments of modern civilization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these are not terribly exciting points to make, it is curious how much of a barrier there is between the public and the scientific papers which are the products of science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or rather, how much of a barrier there was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever obstacles there were in place, the Internet has burned them to the ground and fundamentally changed the informational inequalities that the old system promoted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;substack&quot;&gt; Subscribe to get each new essay delivered to your inbox as its published.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;margin:0px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://lettucebecereal.substack.com/embed&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;100&quot; style=&quot;border:0px solid #EEE; background:fffff8;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, if you were not a researcher or a student, there was no way for you to read scientific papers. For all the lip service payed to science and having a scientific mindset, people have not had until recently the opportunity to see for themselves what it is that scientists actually do. The relationship between the public and science has always been mediated by the media and whatever popularizing activites scientists make, either through general audience books or lectures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the way that the system was structured, there was what could be called a state of informational inequality, whereby a select few have access to the repositories of the world’s scientific knowledge while the large majority of people did not and had to contend themselves with whatever morsels they were fed by the gatekeepers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, that inequality is no longer in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the same incentives that created it are still with us, they can no longer put up much of a fight against the curious mind. Anyone who wishes to read the latest scientific results, or the classics that have defined a field, can now do so. The ideas and insights from some of the brightest minds in the world about everything under the sun are now accessible to everyone with a curious mind and a connection to the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth of the matter is, we have it good these days. If there is any paper we want to read we can do so with no trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone with access to the Internet has free, immediate access to virtually every piece of scientific research that has ever been published. The only issue is that most people, even academics by my experience, have no idea that this is true. They have not been made aware that times have changed and that the gates have been blown wide open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post I want to show you how to take advantage of this new paradigm so that your curious mind is never again prevented from filling itself with the sweet pleasures of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let the torrents of knowledge flow freely!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sci-hub&quot;&gt;Sci-Hub&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is somewhat anticlimactic to note that this post can be boiled down to two words:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use Sci-Hub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sci-Hub has been the greatest influencing force towards a world of informational equality. Started in 2011 by Alexandra Elbakyan, a Kazakhstani programmer, the goal behind Sci-Hub is to make information available to all those who wish to access it. To do that, it uses the user accounts of supporting researchers to get inside the networks of universities around the world to download papers that  it then makes available for anyone to read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it’s true that information wants to be free, then it has found a powerful ally in Sci-hub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is a paper you want to read it is very unlikely you won’t be able to find it with Sci-Hub. &lt;a href=&quot;https://elifesciences.org/articles/32822&quot;&gt;An analysis from 2018&lt;/a&gt; studied how the repository amassed by Sci-Hub until 2017 stacked up against the access provided by the University of Pennsylvania and concluded that Sci-Hub provided a much greater coverage, containing approximately 70% of the 81.6 million scholarly articles that are registered with Crossref. Things can only have gotten better since then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sci-Hub is so good that researchers worldwide, the very people who are supposed to be the ones with the exclusive access to the research literature, use it regularly because it is that much better than what their university provides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if Sci-Hub is so good, how do you go about using it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Using the website:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1 -&lt;/strong&gt; Copy the URL of the paper&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2 -&lt;/strong&gt; Go to www.sci-hub.se&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3 -&lt;/strong&gt; Paste it there and have fun learning about the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s that simple. And it can be even simpler by creating a bookmarklet in your browser that automates the entire process. To create one, follow these steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating a bookmarklet in Firefox:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1 -&lt;/strong&gt; Right-click on the bookmarks toolbar and choose “New Bookmark”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2 -&lt;/strong&gt; In the Location prompt copy-paste the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;javascript:location.href%20=%20location.origin.replace(/^https/,%20’http’)%20+%20’.sci-hub.se’%20+%20location.pathname%20+%20location.search&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3 -&lt;/strong&gt; Save it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating a bookmarklet in Chrome:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1 -&lt;/strong&gt; Right-click on the bookmarks toolbar and choose “New Page”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2 -&lt;/strong&gt; In the URL prompt, copy-paste the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;javascript:location.href%20=%20location.origin.replace(/^https/,%20’http’)%20+%20’.sci-hub.se’%20+%20location.pathname%20+%20location.search&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3 -&lt;/strong&gt; Save it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this bookmarklet does is replace the URL of the page you are in (which would be the page of the paper you want to read) with the the Sci-Hub version of it. Instead of having to copy the URL, travel to the Sci-Hub page, and paste it there, this bookmarklet does all of that automatically. You just click on the bookmark and it will take you there&lt;label for=&quot;sci-hub.tw&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sci-hub.tw&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;If for some reason the website is blocked, substitute where it is written ‘sci-hub.se’ with ‘sci-hub.tw’ &lt;/span&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For almost any paper, Sci-hub will be enough. The remaining tips I have will help if by an unlucky draw of the cards the paper you want to read is one of the few that Sci-Hub does not have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sci-Hub is liberating. In the Greek mythos, Prometheus stole the fire from the gods and gifted it to humans. Sci-Hub is that Promethean enterprise, setting knowledge free from the shackles it has been bound to. To say that Sci-Hub is one of the things in this world I value the most is an understatement. My life would be irrevocably poorer without its existence, and if you are only now discovering it, I am sure that you will in no time agree with me when I say that this website, created by an unassuming Kazakhstani programmer, is one of the gems of the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s just hope that Alexandra doesn’t end up &lt;a href=&quot;https://qz.com/1773765/sci-hub-creator-says-shes-not-working-for-russian-intelligence/&quot;&gt;sharing Prometheus’ rotten fate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;google-scholar&quot;&gt;Google Scholar&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google Scholar is for papers what Google is for the Internet at large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can search papers by title or author, and specify what time period you want the papers to have been published in. You can also enter keywords related to things you are looking for to see if there have been papers published about it. For example, you can search for “episodic memory in animals” at it will show you papers in which those keywords appear. The traditional tips on how to use Google apply here, so using quote markers around a phrase will search for that verbatim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Google Scholar does that is relevant for our purposes here is that if in its process of aggregating websites it finds the PDF of paper available, it will include a link to it in the search results. The selection is not as comprehensive as Sci-Hub, but because Google Scholar is often used in an exploratory fashion when we know what we want to look for but are not entirely sure which papers to read, having those links right at hand is often valuable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Google Scholar doesn’t link to the PDF of the paper you want, you can try searching for it in the regular Google website. Sometimes it might happen that even though the paper is available online, it does not get indexed as such by Google Scholar. In such cases you’re more likely to be able to find it if you get creative with your use of Google by, for example, searching for specific phrases that you know appear in the text. For example, if a paper includes a quote from another paper that you can’t find, searching for that quote might turn up the paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I once found the PDF of an unpublished paper I wanted to read by searching for combinations of the authors’ names and keywords that I thought would appear on the title. That turned up the schedule for a conference the authors were presenting the paper in, which included a Google Drive link to a copy of the paper in it. A little bit of intuition and creativity go a long way here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an aside, one Google Scholar feature that I rarely see people talk about is how you can create alerts for when a paper you enjoyed gets cited by another paper, or an author you like publishes something new. Though the signal to noise ratio can be low, it is a cheap way to introduce some serendipity into your reading process and may point you to things that you wouldn’t otherwise find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;asking-people-for-help&quot;&gt;Asking people for help&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the paper you are looking for isn’t on Sci-Hub, and Google doesn’t turn up anything, the next best avenue to pursue is asking other people if they have it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might mean asking one of the authors of the paper for a copy, or at the very least seeing if they have one available through their website. Researchers generally do a lousy job keeping their personal websites up to date, but it can’t hurt to try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also not every day that a researcher gets a cold email from someone they’ve never met asking for something that they wrote with the expectation that it would only ever be read by the small community of other researchers working on that topic, so you are unlikely to bother them by doing so. Note that this is nothing like asking for an author to send you a copy of his or her book for free. Researchers make no money from published research, even if publishers charge people to access that research, so unless you’re terribly unpleasant in your email, you are more likely to make the researcher just a little bit happier in knowing that someone is interested in their research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If what you’re searching for is from a long time ago and on a particularly obscure topic, then it might be difficult to get the previous strategies to work. For those special cases, as a measure of last resort, you might try sending a distress call into the void of the Internet and wait to see if a kind soul answers your beacon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One place you might try is the r/scholar subreddit, which specializes in those difficult cases. I recall using it successfully before, but it was before Sci-hub was a thing so I don’t have any particular advice on how to use it besides making you aware of its existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now living in an age where the obstacles between your curiosity and the resources with which to satisfy it are no more. Access to knowledge has, finally, been democratized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this post I showed you how you can access for free and without much hassle a vast and ever increasing vault filled to the brim with the knowledge that scientists the world over have labored to unlock. There has never been this much information about the world so widely available and for so many people to enjoy, and it is my sincere hope that this will help you in taking advantage of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t wait to see what you choose to learn with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Alexey Guzey for reading a draft of this.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/howtoreadallpapersforfree</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/howtoreadallpapersforfree</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
